<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<project>
  <id>bigdata</id>
  <name>bigdata</name>
  <package>com.bigdata</package>
  <extends>../bigdata-master-pom/project.xml</extends>
  <groupId>bigdata</groupId>
  <currentVersion>0.1-b1-dev</currentVersion>

  <!-- @todo "master" project, CVSROOT (permissions). -->

  <organization>
    <name>SYSTAP, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.bigdata.com/</url>
    <!--logo>url goes here</logo-->
  </organization>

  <!-- required per-POM metadata. -->
  <inceptionYear>2006</inceptionYear>
  <url>http://www.bigdata.com/</url>
  <!--logo>url goes here</logo-->

  <!-- The short description is used in the JAR manifest.  For -->
  <!-- compatibility reasons, no leading/trailing newlines and -->
  <!-- 72 character length limit.                              -->

  <shortDescription>bigdata(TM)</shortDescription>

  <description>

  <!-- 169 is copyright; 174 is registered mark. -->

<![CDATA[

  <p>

	  bigdata&#169; is a scale-out data and computing fabric designed for commodity hardware. 

  </p>
  <p>

	  The bigdata architecture provides named scale-out indices that are transparently
	  partitioned and distributed across a cluster or grid of commodity server platforms.
	  Atomic "row" operations are supported for very high concurrency.  However, full
	  transactions are also available for applications needing less concurrency but
	  requiring atomic operations that read or write on more than one row, index partition,
	  or index.  The scale-out indices are B+Trees and remain balanced under insert and
	  removal operations.  Keys and values for btrees are variable length byte[]s (the
	  keys are interpreted as unsigned byte[]s).  Writes are absorbed on mutable btree instances in append only
	  "journals" of ~200M capacity.  On overflow, data in a journal is evicted onto read-
	  optimized, immutable "index segments".  The metadata service manages the index 
	  definitions, the index partitions, and the assignment of index partitions to data
	  services.  A data service encapsulates a journal to zero or more index partitions
	  have been assigned, including the logic to handle overflow.  A deployment is made
	  up of one logical metadata service (with failover redundency) and many distinct
	  data services.  bigdata can provide data redundency internally (by pipelining
	  writes bound for a partition across primary, secondary, ... data service instances
	  for that partition) or it can be deployed over distributed RAID.  bigdata itself
	  is 100% Java and requires a 1.5 or better JVM.
	  
  </p>
  
  <h2>Architecture</h2>
  
  <p>
  
  	  The bigdata SOA defines two essential services and some additional services.  The
  	  essential services are the metadata service (provides a locator service for index
  	  partitions on data services) and the data service (provides read, write, and concurrency
  	  control for index partitions). Optional services include a transaction manager (transactions
  	  are NOT required, so you can use bigdata as a scale-out row store ) and a job scheduler (the
  	  integration point for map/reduce style distributed functional programming).  
  
  </p>
  
  <p>
  
  	  While other service fabric architectures are contemplated, bigdata services
  	  today use JINI 2.x to advertise themselves and do perform service discovery.
  	  This means that you must be running a JINI registrar in order for services to be
  	  able to register themselves or discover other services.  The JINI integration is
  	  bundled in a separate module - see <strong>bigdata-jini</strong>.
  
  </p>
  
  <p>
  
  	  The main building blocks for the bigdata architecture are the journal (append-only
  	  persistence store), the mutable B+Tree (used to absorb writes), and the read-optimized
  	  immutable B+Tree (aka the index segment).  Highly efficient bulk index builds are used
  	  to transfer data absorbed by a mutable B+Tree on a journal into index segment files.
  	  Each for index segment contains data for a single partition of a scale-out index.  In
  	  order to read from an index partition, a consistent view is created by dynamically
  	  fusing data for that index partition, including any recent writes on the current
  	  journal, any historical writes that are in the process of being transferred onto
  	  index segments, and any historical index segments that also contain data for that
  	  view.  Periodically, index segments are merged together.  Both merging index segments
  	  and overflow of a journal onto index segments cause historical states of the database
  	  to be purged in favor of the current state.  Periodically, the metadata service will
  	  direct data services to physically delete old journals and index segments, thereby
  	  releasing the local disk resources.  (An immortal or temporal database can be
	  realized by choosing not to delete old journals, since journals have all committed
  	  states for the distributed database.) 
  
  </p>
  
  <h2>Sparse row store</h2>
  
  <p>
  
 	  People familiar with Google's bigtable architecture will recognize the similarity.
 	  bigtable provides very high concurrency with atomic "row" updates and a space data
 	  model.  In fact, it is trivial to realize bigtable semantics with bigdata - you 
 	  need to exercise a specific protocol when forming the keys for your scale-out
 	  indices and you simply choose to NOT use transactions.  A bigtable style key-value
 	  is formed as:

  </p>
  
  <pre>
  
      [columnFamily][primaryKey][columnName][timestamp} : [value]
  
  </pre>
  
  <p>
 	  
 	  By placing the column family identifier up front, all data in the same column
 	  family will be clustered together by the index.  The next component is the "row"
 	  identifier, what you would think of as the primary key in a relational table.
 	  The column name comes next - only column names for non-null columns are written
 	  into the index.  Finally, there is a timestamp column that is used either to
 	  record a timestamp specified by the application or a datum write time.  The
 	  value associated with the key is simply the datum for that column in that row.
 	  The use of nul byte separators makes it possible to parse the key, which is
 	  required for various operations including index partition splits and filtering
 	  key scans based on column names or timestamps.
 	  See the KeyBuilder class
 	  in com.bigdata.btree for utilities that may be used to construct keys from a variety
 	  of components.
  
  </p>
  
  <p>
  
      Filter row scans are realized using the filter mechanism on the key scan
      interface of the data service.  The history policy is specified when the
      index is created and is applied during compacting merges of index segments,
      effectively removing entries for the index partition that do not pass the
      history filter.
  
  </p>

  <h2>Map/reduce</h2>
  
  <p>
  
  	  Google's map/reduce architecture has received a lot of attention, along with
  	  its bigtable architecture.  Map/reduce provides a means to transparently
  	  decompose processing across a cluster.  The "map" process examines a series
  	  of key-value pair, emitting a set of intermediate key-value pairs for each
  	  input.  Those intermediate key-values are then hashed (module R) onto R reduce
  	  processes.  The inputs for the reduce processes are pre-sorted.  The reduce
  	  process then runs some arbitrary operation on the sorted data, such as computing
  	  an inverted index file or loading the data into a scale-out index.
  
  </p>

  <h2>Data Replication</h2>
  
  <p>
  
  	  If you know much about Google's architecture, you know that they deploy on
  	  a distributed file system named "GFS" (Google File System).  bigdata is
  	  designed to provide its own data replication using pipelining of writes
  	  across multiple data services, such that each index partition has some
  	  target #of replicated indices.  However, an alternative deployment strategy
  	  is to deploy on a distributed file system or using NAS with built in RAID.
  	  The best deployment configuration undoubtedly depends on the specifics of
  	  your data center.  bigtable makes an effort throughout its architecture to
  	  only perform sustained IOs.  This means that it can be a very efficient user
  	  of both local file systems and networked file systems.
  
  </p>

  <h2>Embedded database</h2>
  
  <p>
  
  	  While bigdata is targetted at scale-out federations, it can also be deployed as an
  	  embedded database - and embedded federations are available to make testing easier.
  	  The key points when deploying as an embedded database are: (1) that journals MAY
  	  range up to 4T in size; and (2) that the journal is at heart a WORM (Write Once
  	  Read Many) (also known as an immortal database or a log-structured store).  This
  	  means that you have to manage the journal size.  The basic means for doing this
  	  is to export optimized read-only index segments corresponding to either entire
  	  indices or key ranges of indices.  Once no live data remains on a journal it may
  	  be discarded (unless you want an immortal database).  Tools are in the works to
  	  make this process transparent - new journals are opened while indices are exported
  	  from old ones with the net result that the total storage of the database remains
  	  very compact.  (This is similar to the concept of a compacting merge.)
  
  </p>
  
  <h2>Status</h2>
  
  <p>
  	  
  	  The basic index structures (mutable and immutable btrees and
  	  bulk index build operations) and the persistent store
  	  structure (the journal) have all been implemented, tested
  	  and are showing good performance.  The basic distributed
  	  services architecture is up and running, but indices must be
  	  statically range partitioned.  The "sparse row store" API
  	  has been implemented, offering an interface similar to HBase
  	  or bigtable.  The map/reduce services are up and running,
  	  but further performance tuning is required (optimization for
  	  local writes).  Asynchronous overflow of the indices (aka compacting
  	  merge) has been prototyped and needs to be refactored into the main
  	  data service.  Data replication and service failover are
  	  not finished.

	  </p><p>

	  There is an RDF database application layer (bigdata-rdf)
  	  that is being used to benchmark and tune the bigdata
  	  implementation. We have plans to provide an transactional
  	  OODBMS integration (based on the Generic Object Model) as
  	  well as a media index and search service.

	  </p><p>

	  We are seeking beta users to vet the architecture and work
  	  through robust scaling.  
  	  
  </p>
  
  <h2>License</h2>
  
  <p>
  
  	  bigdata is currently being released under GPL (version 2).  However, it is
  	  our intention to make bigdata usable by non-GPL Free/Libre and Open Source
  	  Software (FLOSS) projects.  To this end, we are considering either a FLOSS
  	  exclusion (such as MySQL AB has issued) or a license change to something
  	  with the same semantics as the SleepyCat License.  We are also considering
  	  the Open Software License v 3.0.  Please bear with us while we work through
  	  this issue.  If you have any questions concerning the license, write
  	  <a href="mailto:licenses@bigdata.com">licenses@bigdata.com</a>.
  
  </p>
  
  <p>
  
  	  SYSTAP, LLC offers commercial licenses for customers who either want the
  	  value add (warranty, technical support, additional regression testing), who
  	  want to redistribute bigdata with their own commercial products, or who are
  	  not "comfortable" with the GPL license.  For inquiries or further information,
  	  please write <a href="mailto:licenses@bigdata.com">licenses@bigdata.com</a>.
  
  </p>

  <h2> Related links </h2>

  <p>
  
  <dl>

  <dt>CouchDB</dt>
  <dd>http://couchdb.org/CouchDB/CouchDBWeb.nsf/Home?OpenForm</dd>

  <dt>bigtable</dt>
  <dd>http://labs.google.com/papers/bigtable.html, http://www.techcrunch.com/2008/04/04/source-google-to-launch-bigtable-as-web-service/</dd>

  <dt>map/reduce</dt>
  <dd>http://labs.google.com/papers/mapreduce.html</dd>

  <dt>Hadoop</dt>
  <dd>http://lucene.apache.org/hadoop/</dd>

  <dt>Pig</dt>
  <dd>http://research.yahoo.com/node/90</dd>

  <dt>Sawsall</dt>
  <dd>http://labs.google.com/papers/sawzall.html</dd>

  <dt>Boxwood</dt>
  <dd>http://research.microsoft.com/research/sv/Boxwood/</dd>

  <dt>Blue Cloud</dt>
  <dd>http://www.techcrunch.com/2007/11/15/ibms-blue-cloud-is-web-computng-by-another-name/</dd>

  <dt>SimpleDB</dt>
  <dd>http://www.techcrunch.com/2007/12/14/amazon-takes-on-oracle-and-ibm-with-simple-db-beta/</dd>

  <dt>mg4j</dt>
  <dd>http://mg4j.dsi.unimi.it/</dd>

  </dl>

  </p>

]]>

  </description>

  <versions>
  
  <!-- There is a tag (BIGDATA_FAST_BTREE_BRANCH) and a branch
       (BIGDATA_FAST_BTREE_BRANCH_FOR_REAL) for the version of the
       btree before I added, and then removed, the stride support
       and before I converted to the varable length unsigned byte[]
       keys.  This version is significantly faster for reasons that
       I have not been able to track down yet. -->

  </versions>

  <!-- copy down inheritance applies. -->
  <siteAddress>www.bigdata.com</siteAddress>
  <siteDirectory>
    /home/groups/b/bi/bigd/htdocs/projects/${pom.artifactId}
  </siteDirectory>

  <!-- copy down inheritance applies. -->
  <distributionSite>www.sourceforge.net</distributionSite>
  <distributionDirectory>/projects/bigdata</distributionDirectory>

  <!-- copy down inheritance applies. -->
  <!--
  <issueTrackingUrl>
  http://jira.bigdata.com/browse/bigdata
  </issueTrackingUrl>
  -->
  <issueTrackingUrl>
  http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=191861
  </issueTrackingUrl>

  <!-- copy down inheritance applies. -->
  <repository>
    <connection>
    scm:cvs:pserver:anonymous@${maven.scm.cvs.host}:/cvsroot/bigdata:bigdata
    </connection>
    <developerConnection>
    scm:cvs:ext:user@${maven.scm.cvs.host}:/cvsroot/bigdata:bigdata
    </developerConnection>
    <url>http://bigdata.cvs.sourceforge.net/bigdata/bigdata</url>
  </repository>

  <!-- copy down inheritance applies. -->
  <licenses>
    <license>
      <name>GPL (version 2)</name>
      <url>http://www.opensource.org/licenses/gpl-license.php</url>
      <distribution>manual</distribution>
    </license>
  </licenses>

  <!-- copy down inheritance applies.
  <mailingLists>
    <mailingList>
      <name>Announce List</name>
      <subscribe>
        http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/bigdata-announce
      </subscribe>
      <unsubscribe>
        http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/bigdata-announce
      </unsubscribe>
      <archive>
        http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=bigdata-announce
      </archive>
    </mailingList>
    <mailingList>
      <name>Developer List</name>
      <subscribe>
        http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/bigdata-developer
      </subscribe>
      <unsubscribe>
        http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/bigdata-developer
      </unsubscribe>
      <archive>
        http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=bigdata-developer
      </archive>
    </mailingList>
  </mailingLists>
  -->

  <!-- copy down inheritance applies. -->
  <developers>

    <developer>
      <name>Bryan Thompson</name>
      <id>bryan</id>
      <email>thompsonbry@users.sourceforge.net</email>
      <organization>SYSTAP, LLC.</organization>
      <!-- East coast. -->
      <timezone>-5</timezone>
    </developer>

    <developer>
      <name>Mike Personick</name>
      <id>mike</id>
      <email>mrpersonick@users.sourceforge.net</email>
      <organization>SYSTAP, LLC.</organization>
      <!-- US Mountain. -->
      <timezone>-7</timezone>
    </developer>

  </developers>

  <contributors>
    <!--
    <contributor>
      <name>...</name>
      <id>...</id>
      <email>...</email>
      <organization>...</organization>
    </contributor>
    -->
  </contributors>

  <!-- project-specific data. -->
  <dependencies>

	<!-- Note: Dependencies are bundled in CVS. -->

    <!-- log4j integration. -->
    <dependency> 
      <id>log4j</id> 
      <version>1.2.8</version> 
      <url>http://logging.apache.org</url>
    </dependency>

    <!-- junit (tests only). -->
    <dependency> 
      <id>junit</id> 
      <version>3.8.1</version> 
      <url>http://www.junit.org/</url>
    </dependency>

	<!-- junit extensions (tests only). -->
    <dependency>
      <groupId>org.CognitiveWeb</groupId>
      <artifactId>cweb-junit-ext</artifactId>
      <version>1.1-b3-dev</version>
      <url>http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/cweb</url>
    </dependency>

	<!-- cweb utility classes. -->
    <dependency> 
      <groupId>org.CognitiveWeb</groupId>
      <artifactId>cweb-commons</artifactId>
      <version>1.1-b2-dev</version>
      <url>http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/cweb</url>
    </dependency>

	<!-- Extensible Serialization framework. -->
    <dependency> 
      <groupId>org.CognitiveWeb</groupId>
      <artifactId>cweb-extser</artifactId>
      <version>0.1-b2-dev</version>
      <url>http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/cweb</url>
    </dependency>
   <dependency> 
      <groupId>org.CognitiveWeb</groupId>
      <artifactId>lgpl-utils</artifactId>
      <version>1.0-b1-dev</version>
      <url>http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/cweb</url>
    </dependency>

    <!-- Striterator support. -->
    <!-- Note: The jar name reflects the date when I downloaded it -->
    <!-- and makes it possible for me to rollback to historical CTC -->
    <!-- versions.  Any recent "ctc_utils.jar" SHOULD work.  Just -->
    <!-- extract the JAR and rename it. -->
    <dependency>
      <groupId>ctc</groupId>
      <artifactId>utils</artifactId>
      <jar>ctc_utils-5-4-2005.jar</jar>
      <url>http://www.cutthecrap.biz/downloads/ctc_utils.zip</url>
    </dependency>

	<!-- @todo Use autojar to select only the required classes for redistribution? -->
    <dependency> 
      <groupId>it.unimi</groupId>
      <artifactId>dsiutils</artifactId>
      <version>1.0.4</version>
      <url>http://dsiutils.dsi.unimi.it/</url>
    </dependency>
    <dependency> 
      <groupId>it.unimi</groupId>
      <id>fastutil5</id> 
      <version>5.1.3</version> 
      <url>http://fastutil.dsi.unimi.it/</url>
    </dependency>
    <dependency> 
      <groupId>it.unimi</groupId>
      <id>fastutil5</id> 
      <version>5.1.3</version> 
      <url>http://fastutil.dsi.unimi.it/</url>
    </dependency>
    <!-- dependency used by dsiutils (bloom filter). -->
    <dependency>
       <groupId>com.martiansoftware</groupId>
       <artifactId>jsap</artifactId>
       <version>2.0</version>
	</dependency> 
	<!-- dependency used by dsiutils (bloom filter). -->
	<dependency>
       <groupId>colt</groupId>
	   <artifactId>colt</artifactId>
	   <version>1.2.0</version>
	</dependency> 
    
	<!-- full text indexing support. -->
	<dependency>
	    <groupId>org.apache.lucene</groupId>
	    <artifactId>lucene-core</artifactId>
	    <version>2.2.0</version>
	</dependency> 
	<dependency>
	    <groupId>org.apache.lucene</groupId>
	    <artifactId>lucene-analyzers</artifactId>
	    <version>2.2.0</version>
	</dependency> 

	<!-- ICU provides optional support for compressed Unicode sort keys. -->
    <dependency>
      <groupId>icu</groupId>
      <artifactId>icu4j</artifactId> 
      <version>3_6</version> 
      <url>http://sourceforge.net/projects/icu/</url>
    </dependency>

  </dependencies>

  <build>

    <nagEmailAddress>
      thompsonbry@users.sourceforge.net
    </nagEmailAddress>

    <sourceDirectory>${basedir}/src/java</sourceDirectory>

    <unitTestSourceDirectory>${basedir}/src/test</unitTestSourceDirectory>

    <aspectSourceDirectory/>

    <!-- Unit test cases -->

    <unitTest>

      <includes>
        <include>com/bigdata/TestAll.java</include>
      </includes>

      <!-- Resources for test cases are declared here. -->

    </unitTest>
              
    <!-- J A R  R E S O U R C E S -->
    <resources>
      <resource>
        <directory>${basedir}/src/resources/logging</directory>
        <includes>
          <include>log4j.properties</include>
        </includes>
        <directory>${basedir}/src/resources</directory>
        <includes>
          <include>config/**/*</include>
        </includes>
     </resource>

      <!-- Note: This forces the bundling of unit tests, but ONLY if you run
      	   (or at least build) the unit tests!
      	   
      	   This is being done in order to make the unit tests available to
      	   bigdata-rdf and other projects that wish to extend AbstractServerTestCase.
      <resource>
        <directory>${basedir}/target/test-classes</directory>
        <includes>
          <include>com/bigdata/service/AbstractServerTestCase.class</include>
        </includes>
      </resource>
      	   -->

    </resources>

    <jars>
    </jars>

  </build>

</project>
