<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<web-app xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee/web-app_3_1.xsd"
      version="3.1">
  <servlet>
   <servlet-name>Load Balancer</servlet-name>
   <description>
   The HA Load Balancer servlet provides a transparent proxy for
   requests arriving its configured URL pattern (the "external"
   interface for the load balancer) to the root of the web
   application.  

   The use of the load balancer is entirely optional.  If the
   security rules permit, then clients MAY make requests directly
   against a specific service. Thus, no specific provision exists
   to disable the load balancer servlet, but you may choose not to
   deploy it.

   When successfully deployed, requests having prefix corresponding to
   the URL pattern for the load balancer are automatically redirected
   to a joined service in the met quorum based on the configured load
   balancer policy.
   
   Requests directed to /bigdata/LBS/leader are proxied to the quorum
   leader - this URL must be used for non-idempotent requests
   (updates).
   
   Requests directed to /bigdata/LBS/read are load balanced over the
   services joined with the met quourm.  This URL may only be used
   with idempotent requests (reads).
   
   For non-HA deployments, requests are simply forwarded to the local
   service after stripping off the /LBS/leader or /LBS/read prefix.
   Thus, it is always safe to use the LBS request URLs.

   The load balancer policies are "HA aware." They will always
   redirect update requests to the quorum leader.  The default
   polices will load balance read requests over the leader and
   followers in a manner that reflects the CPU, IO Wait, and GC
   Time associated with each service.  The PlatformStatsPlugIn
   and GangliaPlugIn MUST be enabled for the default load
   balancer policy to operate. It depends on those plugins to
   maintain a model of the load on the HA replication cluster.
   The GangliaPlugIn should be run only as a listener if you are
   are running the real gmond process on the host.  If you are 
   not running gmond, then the GangliaPlugIn should be configured
   as both a listener and a sender.
   </description>
   <servlet-class>com.bigdata.rdf.sail.webapp.HALoadBalancerServlet</servlet-class>
   <load-on-startup>1</load-on-startup>
   <async-supported>true</async-supported>
   <init-param>
      <param-name>policy</param-name>
      <param-value>com.bigdata.rdf.sail.webapp.lbs.policy.RoundRobinLBSPolicy</param-value>
      <description>
      The load balancer policy. This must be an instance of the
      IHALoadBalancerPolicy interface.  A default policy (NOPLBSPolicy) is
      used when no value is specified. 
      
      The policies differ ONLY in how they handle READ requests. All policies
      proxy updates to the leader. If you do not want update proxying, then 
      use a URL that does not address the HALoadBalancerServlet.
      
      The following policies are pre-defined:
      
      com.bigdata.rdf.sail.webapp.lbs.policy.NOPLBSPolicy:
      
         Does not load balance read requests.
      
      com.bigdata.rdf.sail.webapp.lbs.policy.RoundRobinLBSPolicy:
      
         Round robin for read requests.
      
      com.bigdata.rdf.sail.webapp.lbs.policy.counters.CountersLBSPolicy:
      
         Load based proxying for read requests using the build in http
         service for reporting performance counters.  This policy requires
         the PlatformStatsPlugIn and may also require platform specific
         metrics collection dependencies, e.g., sysstat.

      com.bigdata.rdf.sail.webapp.lbs.policy.ganglia.GangliaLBSPolicy:
      
         Load based proxying for read requests using ganglia. This policy
         requires the requires the PlatformStatsPlugIn.  In addition, either
         gmond must be installed on each node or the embedded GangliaService
         must be enabled such that performance metrics are collected and
         reported.
      
      Some of these policies can be further configured using additional
      init-param elements that they understand. See the javadoc for the
      individual policies for more information.
      </description>
   </init-param>
  </servlet>
  <servlet-mapping>
    <servlet-name>Load Balancer</servlet-name>
    <url-pattern>/LBS/*</url-pattern>
  </servlet-mapping>
</web-app>
